A Guide to the William Crutchfield Business Records, 1848-1870
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
William Crutchfield Business Records, 1848-1870
The Library of Virginia
1107270, 1107271, 1107276, 1107280, 1107282, 1107284, 1107287, 1107288, 1107291, 1107304, 1128725, 1128735-1128738
15 volumes (Three daybooks are in poor condition due to missing covers and damaged spines. Two ledgers are in poor condition due to damaged spines. One account book is in poor condition due to torn spine)
Goochland County
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These materials came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Goochland County.
Historical Information
William Crutchfield was a merchant who, on his own or in partnership with others, owned general stores in the towns of Rocketts, Cedar Point, and Merry Oaks in Goochland County, Virginia, during the mid- nineteenth century. He also perhaps owned a blacksmith shop in Cedar Point that was worked by blacksmith Olonzo C. Cantrell.
Scope and Content Information
Six daybooks, four ledgers, three account books, one journal, and one statement book used to record the financial activities of several businesses owned by William Crutchfield of Goochland County, Virginia.
Three daybooks, one dated December 1851-January 1853, the second dated September 1853-August 1855, and the third dated March 1857-February 1859, that record the daily transactions of Crutchfield's store in Rocketts. Information found in entries includes name of customer, date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Entries correspond with entries with similar dates found in Account Book, 1849-1856, Journal 1851-1857, and Ledger, 1853-1858.
Account book, 1849-1856, used as a ledger and a daybook at Crutchfield's store in Rocketts. The ledger portion of the volume records the accounts of individual customers. One set of accounts lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash, credit, or barter of items such as eggs and butter. Entries for 1852 correspond with entries for 1852 in Daybook, December 1851-January 1853. The second set of accounts in volume lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, style of transaction, and amount owed and paid. Entries do not list the names of items purchased; rather, they use the general term "amount of bill." The daybook portion of the volume records the daily transactions of Crutchfield's store in Rocketts from August to October 1855. Information found in entries includes name of customer, date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Volume also records the payments of bonds by individuals and the store's controlling accounts, such as cash account and bills payable account. Volume includes an index that lists customers in alphabetical order and the page numbers where their accounts can be found.
Journal, 1851-1857, and Ledger, 1853-1858, record the accounts of individual customers of Crutchfield's store in Rocketts. Transactions are listed in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash, credit, or barter of items such as eggs and leather. Entries in the journal and ledger correspond with entries found in Daybook, December 1851-January 1853, Daybook, September 1853-August 1855, daybook portion of Account Book, 1849-1856, and Daybook, March 1857-February 1859. Ledger, 1853-1858, also records the payments of bonds by individual and payments of bills by customers.
Statement book, 1855-1858, records varying accounts of Crutchfield's store in Rocketts. One set of accounts include bond accounts of customers. It lists the name of individual, amount of bond, and whether individual paid or not. A separate listing for Negro accounts is included with an additional category for how well or how poorly the individual was in repaying his or her bond. A second set of accounts records the accounts of individual customers. Transactions are listed in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash, credit, or barter of items such as eggs and hogs. Entries for 1853-1855 correspond with entries found in Daybook, September 1853-August 1855.
Account book, 1848-1864, used by Crutchfield as a ledger and a daybook. The ledger portion of the volume records the accounts of individual customers from 1848 to 1856 of Crutchfield's store in Rocketts. Transactions are listed in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash, credit, or barter of items such as eggs, butter, and beeswax. Volume includes inventories of the store's goods for December 1849 and October 1854. Information found in each entry includes name of item, price of each item, and the total amount, both quantity and value, of each item. There is also an inventory of the store's goods at Cedar Point for April 1863. It simply lists the item and the total number of item. The daybook portion of the volume records the transactions of a warehouse or store owned by Crutchfield in Cedar Point from November 1863 to January 1865. Transactions relate to the storage of goods by Crutchfield on behalf of individuals. Information found in entries includes name of customer, date of transaction, items stored, quantity of items stored, cost for storing item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Items stored include salt, flour, meat, tobacco, and furniture. Volume has two separate listings of Negro accounts. Each entry includes individual's name and amount owed to the store. Volume includes an index that lists customers in alphabetical order and the page numbers where their accounts can be found.
Account book, 1857-1868, used as a ledger and a daybook. The ledger portion of the volume records the accounts of individual customers of Crutchfield's store in Merry Oaks in 1857 and 1858. Transactions are listed in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash, credit, or barter of items such as eggs, coonskin, and beef. Volume also records the payments of bonds owed the store by individuals. The daybook portion of the volume records the daily transactions of a store or warehouse owned by Crutchfield in Cedar Point from April 1865 to August 1868. Transactions relate to the storage of goods by Crutchfield on behalf of individuals. Information found in entries includes name of customer, date of transaction, items stored, quantity of items stored, cost of storing item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Items stored include flour, guano, corn, salt, whiskey, safes, various size boxes, sugar, and meat. Volume includes an index that lists customers in alphabetical order and the page numbers where their accounts can be found.
Three daybooks, one dated July 1866-June 1867, the second dated June 1867-June 1869, and the third dated July 1869-January 1870, that record the daily transactions of Crutchfield's store in Cedar Point. Information found in entries includes name of customer, date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash, credit, labor, and barter of items such as corn, eggs, and meal. The last few pages contain information related to the sale of items following Crutchfield's death. Entries in Daybook, July 1866-June 1867, and Daybook, June 1867-June 1869, correspond with entries with similar dates found in Ledger, 1865-1869, and Ledger, 1869-1870.
Two ledgers, one dated 1865-1869, and the second dated 1869-1870, that recordss the accounts of individual customers of Crutchfield's store in Cedar Point. Transactions are listed in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, cost of each item, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash, credit, or barter of items such as oats, onion cloves, butter, and bacon. Entries in ledgers correspond with entries found in Daybook, July 1866-June 1867, Daybook, June 1867-June 1869, and Daybook, July 1869-January 1870. Ledger, 1865-1869, includes an index that lists customers in alphabetical order and the page numbers where their accounts can be found.
Ledger, 1861-1868, used as a freight record book and blacksmith account book. Freight record portion of volume records expenses and cash received from transportion of merchandise by river for January-July 1861. Information found in expense accounts include date of transaction, type of expense, and amount paid. Expenses include labor costs, tolls, and quantity of merchandise transported. The cash received accounts record payments received from customers to cover transportation costs of merchandise incurred by store. Information found in entries include date of payment, name of customer, name of merchandise, and amount of payment received. The blacksmith portion of volume records the accounts of individual customers of a blacksmith shop from 1862 to 1868, perhaps located in Cedar Point. Transactions are listed in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes date of transaction, items purchased or services rendered, quantity of items purchased, cost of item or service, form of payment, and total amount owed and paid. Payments made by cash and credit. Services rendered include shoeing horses and mules, sharpening farm tools, repairing saddles and wagons, and drilling holes in saws. Items sold include horseshoes, keys for yokes, chain links, bolts, and screws. An index is found at the end of blacksmith portion of volume that lists the blacksmith shop's customers in alphabetical order, the page numbers where their accounts can be found, and the total amount each customer owed.
Items sold at Crutchfield's stores include dry goods, whiskey, food, herrings, candles, umbrellas, matches, candy, nails, clothing, knives, violin strings, cologne, scissors, dictionaries, soap, paper, coffee, spoons, shoes, and spices.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional loose records related to William Crutchfield's business activities can be found at the Library of Virginia.
Contents List
- William Crutchfield Daybook, 1851 December-1853 January, 268 p.
- William Crutchfield Daybook, 1853 September-1855 August, 644 p.
- William Crutchfield Daybook, 1857 March-1859 February, 358 p.
- William Crutchfield Daybook, 1866 July-1867 June, 433 p.
- William Crutchfield Daybook, 1867 June-1869 June, 689 p.
- William Crutchfield Daybook, 1869 July-1870 January, 282 p.
- William Crutchfield Ledger, 1853-1858, 622 p.
- William Crutchfield Ledger, 1861-1868, 251 p.
- William Crutchfield Ledger, 1865-1869, 180 p.
- William Crutchfield Ledger, 1869-1870, 159 p.
- Crutchfield and Nicholas Account Book, 1848-1864, 445 p.
- William Crutchfield Account Book, 1849-1856, 672p.
- William Crutchfield Account Book, 1857-1868, 269 p.
- William Crutchfield Journal, 1851-1857, 470 p.
- William Crutchfield Statement Book, 1855-1858, 126 p.